Princeton Ethiopic Manuscripts, late 1600s-1900s: Finding Aid C0776
Manuscripts Division
Princeton Ethiopic Manuscripts
1600s-1900s
Manuscripts Division
Princeton University. Library. Special Collections
C0776
79 manuscripts
An open collection of bound Ethiopic manuscripts with texts in Ge'ez and occasionally in Amharic.
Biographical / Historical
Beginning with the gift of the Robert Garrett Collection in 1942, the Princeton University Library continues to acquire Ethiopic manuscripts by means of purchase or gift.
Scope and Contents
This is an open collection of Ethiopic codices (bound manuscripts), which are chiefly written in Ge'ez (sometimes called Ethiopic), the scholarly and liturgical Afroasiatic language of Ethiopian Orthodox Church, as well as five related items. Many of the Ge'ez manuscripts have varia or marginalia in Amharic; two texts are mostly Amharic. Included among the Ethiopic manuscripts are 16 Psalters, 7 Miracles of Mary, 6 Images, 4 prayer books, 3 Homilies of Michael, 3 Synaxariums, 2 Anaphoras of Mary, 2 antiphonaries, 2 Missals, 1 Gospel of John, and 1 collection of divination texts. Worthy of special note are the variant Miracles of Mary and a rare Cycle of the Kings.
Most of the manuscripts in this collection date from the nineteenth and twentieth century. But at least ten are probably from the eighteenth century, and at least one (Miracles of Mary) is probably from the seventeenth. Precise dating of Ethiopic manuscripts remains difficult. Texts are written in black and red ink on parchment; one manuscript is paper. The manuscripts are bound in a traditional style reminiscent of early Coptic Christian codices in Roman and Byzantine Egypt, for which reason they are sometimes characterized as "Coptic." The quires of the manuscripts are sewn with unsupported link-stitch and then laced into rough-hewn wooden boards, sometimes covered in leather, often blind-tooled. A number of manuscripts are in leather carrying cases, which allowed them to be worn over the shoulder or hung up on pegs in walls.
Arrangement
Arranged in manuscript number order, by accession. Numbers 29 and 67-71 are unassigned.
Conditions Governing Access
Mss No. 54, 57, and 65 are stored in a special vault. Consult curator for access.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These manuscripts were acquired individually by gift or purchase. Since the 1990s, Bruce C. Willsie (Princeton Class of 1986) has donated the following manuscripts: nos. 37, 40-53, 58-64, and 72-85.
Appraisal
No appraisal information is available.
Related Materials
In addition to Princeton Ethiopic codices, the Library also has a collection entitled Garrett Ethiopic Manuscripts (C0744.03), gift of Robert Garrett (Princeton Class of 1897). There is one Ethiopic manuscript in The Scheide Library (Manuscript 119).
The Library also has three substantial collections of Ethiopic magic scrolls. Professor David Appleyard, School of Oriental and African Studies, London, compiled the online checklist of these scrolls, with support from the David A. Gardner '69 Magic Project, Princeton University.
Bibliography
Ephraim Isaac, "Princeton Collection of Ethiopic Manuscripts," Princeton University Library Chronicle 42:1 (Autumn 1980), pp. 33-52. Richard Pankhurst, "Secular Themes in Ethiopian Ecclesiastical Manuscripts: V.: A Catalogue of Illustrations of Historical and Ethnographic Interest in Princeton University Library and Art Gallery," Journal of Ethiopian Studies 22 (November 1989), pp. 31-64. Don C. Skemer, "Princeton's Ethiopic Manuscript Collections at 100," Princeton University Library Chronicle 71:3 (Spring 2010), pp. 461-466.
Manuscripts, Ethiopic.; Psalters - -Ethiopia.; Africa
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 1: Psalter. Dawit, 1800s; 1; 135 folios 1 col. [3r-135r], 21 lines; 2 col. [1r-2v, 135v], 21 lines. Parchment Codex. Wooden boards; the upper stamped leather board is original to the manuscript, the lower wooden board (without leather) is broken and sewn; stitched and open spine. Loose binding and some folios damaged, probably by water. Written in black and red ink. Leather case with detached strap. 19 x 18 cm (Unitid 1)
  Scope and Contents
  An incomplete Psalter. The usual books Gate of Light and Praise of Mary are missing, except for the first page from Praise of Mary, of the Monday section (135v), and a few pages from the Thursday section (1r-2v).
  Fols. 2v, 3r, 4r, 69v, 70r, passim: Upper and lower margin scrawls in crude hand on many folios.
  Fols. 70r-74r: Psalm 86, 87, 88, 89 numbered as 76, 77, 78, 79.
  No owner listed.
  No scribe listed.
  No miniatures.
  No musical notation.
  Bibliography
  References: For a full discussion of the Ethiopic Psalter, see the "Dawit" entry in Encyclopedia Aethiopica, vol. 1, pp.278-279. For a print Ge'ez version of Dawit, see Mäzmurä Dawit, Bərhanənna Sälam Press, Addis Ababa, 1959 EC. For information on the individual books of Dawit, see the following. Regarding the Song of Songs, see H. C. Gleave, The Ethiopic Version of the Song of Songs, London 1951. Regarding the Praise of Mary and Gate of Light, see Karl Fries, Weddâsê Mârjâm. Ein äthiopischer Lobgesang an Maria, Uppsala, 1892; Bernard Velat, Etudes sur le Me'eraf (Paris: 1966), vol. 1, pp. 76–91; vol. 2, pp. 284–96; E. A. Wallis Budge, Legend of Our Lady Mary the Perpetual Virgin and Her Mother Hannâ, Oxford, 1933, pp. 279–96; Christopher Lash, "Gate of Light An Ethiopian Hymn to the Blessed Virgin," Eastern Church Review 4, 1972,36-46; 5, 1973, 143-56.
  - Psalms, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 3r-116r. (Unitid 1)
    Psalm 118 does not include additions about the spiritual meanings of the Hebrew Alphabet.
  - Canticles of the Prophets of the Old and New Testaments, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 116v-128v. (Unitid 1)
  - Song of Songs, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 128v-135r. (Unitid 1)
  - Excerpts of Praise of Mary, Wəddase Maryam, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 1r-2v, 135v. (Unitid 1)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 2: Psalter. Dawit, 1800s; 2; 130 folios 1 col. [4r-113r], 27 lines; 2 col. [113r-130r], 26 lines. Parchment Codex. Wooden boards in stamped red leather, stitched and open spine. Written in black and red ink. One miniature. Two-part leather case with leather strap. 17 x 12 cm (Unitid 2)
  Illustration: Fol. 2v: Drawing of angel with drawn sword, in red and black ink, in a later hand.
  Fol. 1v: Pen scrawl and note of later ownership, without name, in a later hand.
  Fols. 1v-2r: Original text erased.
  Fol. 3r: Pen trial.
  Fol. 3v: Pen scrawls.
  Fol. 94v: The later buyer and seller of the manuscript, as well as the witness and guarantor, are mentioned. The buyer is Mäməre Täkəlä Haymanot and his wife Amätä Yohannəs. The seller is Abunä Gäbrä Egzi'abəher. It includes a warning against theft and the price: five birr. The new owner lists twelve of his family members.
  Fol. 130r: Note of ownership in later hand again mentioning Abunä Täkəlä Haymanot and Amätä Yohannəs.
  Manuscript has pen trials and crude outlines of a horse or head on about two dozen folios.
  The Psalter daily readings are marked on the relevant pages at the top of the folio in another hand.
  Loose folio, a photocopy of a letter in English dated Princeton, July 1, 1976, noting the cost of the manuscript and asking for reimbursement of shipping costs. Letter states that the author plans to visit the Ethiopian collection "now that I know some of the cognate language Tigrinya, which uses the same alphabet." From John to Mr. [Alfred?] Bush.
  References: See references listed in manuscript no. 1.
  - Nicene Creed, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 2r. (Unitid 2)
    In faint blue ink, in a later hand.
  - Concluding Prayer, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 2r. (Unitid 2)
    First two lines of the text on the page are a genealogical list of a particular family, in a later hand.
    Concluding prayer of Psalter in crude, later hand.
  - Psalms, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 4r-94v. (Unitid 2)
    Fol. 51v: Mid section of the Psalms identified with a decorated Ethiopic number 60.
    Fols. 77v-82v: Psalm 118 does include additions about the spiritual meanings of the Hebrew Alphabet.
  - Excerpts of Unidentified Texts, Probably Image of Egzi'abəher Ab, Image of the Holy Savior, and Image of the Icon of Mary, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 95rv. (Unitid 2)
    In another, crude hand. See also Fol. 130v.
  - Canticles of the Prophets of the Old and New Testaments, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 96-106v. (Unitid 2)
  - Song of Songs, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 106v-113r. (Unitid 2)
  - Praise of Mary (Wəddase Maryam), 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 113r-123v. (Unitid 2)
    - Monday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 113r-114r. (Unitid 2)
    - Tuesday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 114r-115v. (Unitid 2)
    - Wednesday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 115v-117v. (Unitid 2)
    - Thursday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 117v-119v. (Unitid 2)
    - Friday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 119v-121r. (Unitid 2)
    - Saturday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 121r-122r. (Unitid 2)
    - Sunday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 122r-123v. (Unitid 2)
  - Gate of Light, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 123v-128v. (Unitid 2)
  - Image of Edom, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 128v-130r. (Unitid 2)
  - Excerpts of Unidentified Texts, Probably Image of Egzi'abəher Ab, Image of the Holy Savior, and Image of the Icon of Mary, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 130v. (Unitid 2)
    In another, crude hand. See also Fol. 95rv.
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 3: Psalter. Dawit, 1900s; 3; 157 folios 1 col. [3r-142r], 22 lines; 2 col. [142v-157r], 22 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Two-part leather case with leather strap. Wooden boards in stamped red leather with covered spine. 17 x 13 cm (Unitid 3)
  Fols. 3r, 157v: Later owner's name appears in pencil and pen, Haläqa Kiros Zägäyä.
  Fol. 1v: Pen trial.
  Fol. 2v: In crude hand, practice writing of Psalm 1.
  Fol. 157r: Pen trial and the salutation of a letter.
  fol. 157v: Pen scrawl.
  Manuscript has pen trials on about two dozen folios.
  The Psalter daily readings are marked on the relevant pages in a later hand at the top of the folio, "For Monday reading," etc.
  - Canticle, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 1v. (Unitid 3)
    In crude hand, in pencil, the first four lines of the Canticle of the Psalter.
  - Magical Prayer Against Snake Bite, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 1v. (Unitid 3)
    Magical Prayer against snake bite in a later hand.
  - Psalms, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 3r-123r. (Unitid 3)
  - Canticles of the Prophets of the Old and New Testaments, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 123r-135v. (Unitid 3)
  - Song of Songs, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 135v-142r. (Unitid 3)
  - Praise of Mary (Wəddase Maryam), 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 142v-152v. (Unitid 3)
    - Monday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 142v-143v. (Unitid 3)
    - Tuesday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 143v-145r. (Unitid 3)
    - Wednesday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 145r-146v. (Unitid 3)
    - Thursday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 146v-149r. (Unitid 3)
    - Friday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 149r-150r. (Unitid 3)
    - Saturday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 150v-151v. (Unitid 3)
    - Sunday, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 151v-152v. (Unitid 3)
  - Gate of Light, 1900s; multiple folios; Located on folio 152v-157r. (Unitid 3)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 4: Psalter. Dawit, circa 1770-1830; 4; 159 folios 1 col. [2r-145r], 19 lines; 2 col. [145v-158v], 19 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Plain wooden boards, fragment of upper board missing, lower board broken and sewn. Stitched and open spine. Loose binding. 20 x 17 cm (Unitid 4)
  Illustrations: fols. 2r, 24v, 43v, 65v, 124r: Häräg (headpieces).
  Fol. 1v: In crude hand, Ge'ez alphabet.
  Manuscript has pen trials on about a dozen folios.
  - Text of the Image of the Archangel Saint Gabriel, circa 1770-1830; multiple folios; Located on folio 1r. (Unitid 4)
    In faded ink, almost illegible, in another hand. See also Fol. 159rv.
  - Psalms, circa 1770-1830; multiple folios; Located on folio 2r-123v. (Unitid 4)
    Fol. 65v: Mid-point of the Psalms marked with a Häräg and the words "half of Psalms".
    Psalm 118 does include additions about the spiritual meanings of the Hebrew Alphabet.
  - Canticles of the Prophets of the Old and New Testaments, circa 1770-1830; multiple folios; Located on folio 124r-138v. (Unitid 4)
  - Song of Songs, circa 1770-1830; multiple folios; Located on folio 138v-145r. (Unitid 4)
  - Praise of Mary (Wəddase Maryam), circa 1770-1830; multiple folios; Located on folio 145v-154v. (Unitid 4)
    - Monday, circa 1770-1830; multiple folios; Located on folio 145v-146r. (Unitid 4)
    - Tuesday, circa 1770-1830; multiple folios; Located on folio 146r-148v. (Unitid 4)
    - Wednesday, circa 1770-1830; multiple folios; Located on folio 148v-149v. (Unitid 4)
    - Thursday, circa 1770-1830; multiple folios; Located on folio 149v-151v. (Unitid 4)
    - Friday, circa 1770-1830; multiple folios; Located on folio 151v-152v. (Unitid 4)
    - Saturday, circa 1770-1830; multiple folios; Located on folio 152v-153v. (Unitid 4)
    - Sunday, circa 1770-1830; multiple folios; Located on folio 153v-154v. (Unitid 4)
  - Gate of Light, circa 1770-1830; multiple folios; Located on folio 154v-158v. (Unitid 4)
  - Text of the Image of the Archangel Saint Gabriel, circa 1770-1830; multiple folios; Located on folio 159rv. (Unitid 4)
    In faded ink, almost illegible, in another hand. See also Fol. 1r.
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 5: Psalter. Dawit, 1800s; 5; 2 folios 1 col., 19 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. No binding 17 x 19 cm (Unitid 5)
  An incomplete Psalter. Manuscript is a fragment of two folios from the same piece of parchment.
  - Psalm 38-40, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 1rv. (Unitid 5)
  - Psalm 47-49, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 2rv. (Unitid 5)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 6: Psalter. Dawit, 1800s; 6; 151 folios 1 col. [3r-137v], 21 lines; 2 col. [138r-150v], 23 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Fols. 1r, 2v: Blank. Two miniatures. No case. Glossy wooden boards, stitched and open spine. 13 x 18 cm (Unitid 6)
  Illustration: Fol. 1v: Miniature of King David playing the harp.
  Illustration: Fol. 2r: Miniature of the Virgin Mary with the Christ Child and two angels with drawn swords.
  Unnumbered folded quarter folio at front of the manuscript, part of binding, has a pen trial and a list of the moveable feasts days.
  Fols. 68v, 69v: In a crude later hand, "This Psalter belongs to Mäməre Kase."
  Musical notation.
  Loose folio that appears to be an address from a delivery box. It states "From: Paul L. Billy / 1501 N. E. 62nd Street/ (Pine Crest Media Center) / Fort Lauderdale, Florida, 33334".
  - Psalms, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 3r-121r. (Unitid 6)
  - Canticles of the Prophets of the Old and New Testaments, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 121r-132r. (Unitid 6)
  - Song of Songs, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 132r-137v. (Unitid 6)
  - Praise of Mary (Wəddase Maryam), 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 138r-147r. (Unitid 6)
    - Monday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 138rv. (Unitid 6)
    - Tuesday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 138v-140r. (Unitid 6)
    - Wednesday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 140r-141v. (Unitid 6)
    - Thursday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 141v-143v. (Unitid 6)
    - Friday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 143v-144v. (Unitid 6)
    - Saturday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 144v-145v. (Unitid 6)
    - Sunday, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 145v-147r. (Unitid 6)
  - Gate of Light, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 147r-150v. (Unitid 6)
  - Excerpt from Psalter, 1800s; multiple folios; Located on folio 151rv. (Unitid 6)
    Psalm 71: 3-24 [to the end], probably from another manuscript (folio is of a smaller size). Folio has been flipped; text begins on the verso and continues on the recto.
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 7: Image of Saint George (Mälkə'a Giyorgis), Image of the Christian Sabbath (Mälkə'a Sänbätä Kərəstiyan), circa 1870-1945; 7; 32 folios 1 col, 10 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Two-part leather case with strap. Wooden boards covered with khaki fabric. 10.5 x 13.5 cm (Unitid 7)
  Illustration: Fol. 1r: Häräg.
  Fols. 8v, 11rv, 12r, 31r, passim: Pencil scrawls.
  Fol. 31v: Ge'ez alphabet in another hand.
  Late 19th century, with 20th-century additions.
  References: Regarding information on the unique Ethiopian genre of Images, see the "Mälkə'a" entry in Encyclopedia Aethiopica, vol. 3, pp. 700. Regarding information on over 300 individual Images, see the magisterial work by Marius Chaîne, "Répertoire des sälam et de malk'e contenus dans les manuscrits éthiopiens des bibliothéques d'Europe." ROC, 2e série, 8, 18 (1913): 183–205 and 337–357. For a print Ge'ez version, Säbattu Kidanat. Qəddase Maryam Mälkə'a Guba'e. Täsfa Press, Addis Ababa 1959 E.C.
  - Image of Saint George, Zä-Säleda Mogäs, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 1r-22r. (Unitid 7)
    (Chaîne, "Répertoire," No. 208)
  - Image of the Christian Sabbath, Mälkə'a Sänbätä Kərəstiyan, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 22v-28v. (Unitid 7)
    (Chaîne, "Répertoire," No. 170)
  - Hymn to the Church, Sälam Läki Betä Kərəstiyan, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 28v-31r. (Unitid 7)
  - Excerpts from the Book of Hours, Lä-Adam Fasikahu, 1945; multiple folios; Located on folio 31v-32v. (Unitid 7)
    In crude hand with the date "Säne 26, '37" EC (June 1945).
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 8: Miracles of Mary (Tä'amrä Maryam), late 19th century; 8; 46 folios 2 cols, 14 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. Wooden boards missing, stitched and open spine. Folios missing at the beginning of the ms. Fol. 22r: Second column blank. Fols. 22v, 38v: Blank. fols. 46rv: One quarter of folio is torn and missing at the top. 12 x 14.5 cm (Unitid 8)
  Fols. 10v, 12v, 25r, 27r: Owner's named erased at the beginning of every miracle, but appears faintly on these folios as "Zä'ra Krəstos."
  Fol. 47: Previous cataloger says this folio loose, but no folio 47 is in the box.
  Manuscript is in different hands, one hand for 1r-22v (miracles 1-12), another for fols. 22r-46v (miracles 13-27). The two parts were commissioned at the same time, however, as the same owner's name appears throughout and the numbering of the miracles is continuous.
  References: The main work addressing the Ethiopic Miracles of Mary is Enrico Cerulli, Il libro etiopico dei Miracoli di Maria (Rome, 1943). Regarding information on Marian literature, see the entry in Encyclopedia Aethiopica, vol. 3, pp. 814-817. For other cataloguing, see S. Strelcyn, Catalogue of Ethiopian Manuscripts in the British Library Acquired Since the year 1877 (London: British Library, 1978), mss. 14, 15, 32, 35, 39. For translations into English, see Wallis Budge, The Miracles of the Blessed Virgin Mary and the Life of Hanna (London 1900); Wallis Budge, One Hundred and Ten Miracles of Our Lady Mary (London 1923); Wallis Budge, Legends of Our Lady Mary, the Perpetual Virgin and Her Mother Hanna (London 1922). For comparison, see one hundred miracles of Mary written down by Johannes Herolt in Latin in the 1430s, the most popular European print version of the tales. For a translation, see C. C. Swinton Bland, Miracles of the Blessed Virgin Mary by Johannes Herolt called Discipulus (1435-1440) (London, George Routledge and Sons, 1928). See also Mussafia, Studien zu den mitteralterlichen Marienlegenden, an examination of collections of Mary legends in European libraries.
  - First Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 1r-2r. (Unitid 8)
    How the Virgin Mary accepted the book of her miracles compiled by Saint Hildefonsus [Däqsəyos], Bishop of Toledo and how she punished a bishop who usurped the garment and chair of Hildefonsus (Budge, Mary 1; Strelcyn 15.1.1, 32.16.1; Bland 1). Incomplete at the beginning.
  - Second Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 2r-4r. (Unitid 8)
    How the Virgin Mary healed the sick deacon who recited her sälam song by anointing him with her breast milk (not in Budge).
  - Third Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 4r-6r. (Unitid 8)
    How the Virgin Mary saved a certain bandit from hanging because he always recited her sälam song and how he became a pious monk (not in Budge).
  - Fourth Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 6r-8v. (Unitid 8)
    How Sybil the prophetess saw a vision of the Virgin Mary holding her child within a circle around the sun and revealed this vision to a king who refused to be worshipped (not in Budge).
  - Fifth Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 9r-10v. (Unitid 8)
    How the Virgin Mary commanded a deacon to dig up and rebury in consecrated ground the body of an adulterous deacon from the island of Jericho in the city of Gärisat who was killed by the people (Budge, Mary, 103).
  - Sixth Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 10v-12v. (Unitid 8)
    How a certain sinful knight from Afəras (France) named Niqodimos recited the Hail Mary (Sälamä Gäbrə'el) his whole life and when he died a tree with Hail Mary written on its leaves in gold sprang from his grave (Budge, Mary, 38).
  - Seventh Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 12v-13v. (Unitid 8)
    How the Virgin Mary kept alive a certain wicked man who had been beaten by his enemies until he repented from his sins.
  - Eighth Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 13v-15v. (Unitid 8)
    How the Virgin Mary gave a garment to a certain bishop and how she commanded him to receive a person who wanted to repent before him (Budge, Mary, 40).
  - Ninth Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 14v-17v. (Unitid 8)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared to a certain deacon who loved to sing her praises and how she received his soul into paradise.
  - Tenth Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 117v-19v. (Unitid 8)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared to a bishop to restore a priest called Enədrəyas who knew how to conduct only one of the fourteen anaphoras, the Anaphora of the Virgin Mary (Budge, Mary, 102).
  - Eleventh Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 19v-21r. (Unitid 8)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared to reassure an ascetic woman about the purity of her friends, other ascetic women in the monastery.
  - Twelfth Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 21r-22r. (Unitid 8)
    How the Virgin Mary appeared as a shining woman and saved the drunk monk, who was devoted to the Virgin Mary, from the lion (Budge, Mary, 48).
  - Thirteenth Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; multiple folios; Located on folio 23r-25r. (Unitid 8)
    How the Virgin Mary confronted robbers who went to steal property from a church devoted to her in Sam and how she locked the door so they couldn't get out and killed one and sent the governor to kill the rest.